<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<article>
<artheader>
	<title>FvwmTabs</title>
	<author>Scott Smedley</author>
	<titleabbrev>FvwmTabs</titleabbrev>
	<date>&releasedate;</date>
</artheader>

<section id="name">
<title>Name</title>
<para><emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> is a generic tabbing module for the FVWM window manager.</para>
</section>


<section id="synopsis">
<title>Synopsis</title>
<para><emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> is spawned by FVWM, so no command line invocation is possible.</para>
</section>


<section id="description">
<title>Description</title>
<para>The <emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> module is capable of swallowing any FVWM window &amp; treating it as a tab in a <emphasis>tab-manager</emphasis> window. A tab-manager is sometimes called a <emphasis>tabber</emphasis>. Each tab-manager can store any number of windows, each in its own <emphasis>tab</emphasis>. The number of tab-managers is limited only by system resources. Tab-managers can even be nested/swallowed within other tab-managers. (ie. a tab-manager can be added as an individual tab to another tab-manager.)</para>
</section>

<section id="invocation">
<title>Invocation</title>
<para><emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> can be invoked by inserting the line:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Module"/> FvwmTabs
</programlisting>

<para>in your .fvwmrc file. This can be placed on a line by itself, if <emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> is to be spawned during FVWM's initialization, or can be bound to a menu, mouse button or keystroke to invoke it later.</para>
</section>

<section id="dependencies">
<title>Installing Dependencies</title>
<para><emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> requires 2 CPAN modules (that are NOT distributed with FVWM) to be installed on your system. They are <emphasis>Tk</emphasis> and <emphasis>X11::Protocol</emphasis>.</para>

<para>They are available at: <ulink>http://search.cpan.org/CPAN/authors/id/N/NI/NI-S/Tk-804.027.tar.gz</ulink> and <ulink>http://search.cpan.org/~smccam/X11-Protocol-0.56/</ulink>.</para>

<para>To install either package:</para>
<programlisting>
tar zxvf $name.tar.gz ; cd $name ; perl Makefile.PL ; make install
</programlisting>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> will tell you if you do not have these packages installed when you (try to) start it.</para>
</section>

<section id="options">
<title>Configuration Options</title>
<para><emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> reads the same config file as FVWM when it starts up.</para>

<para>The following options are recognised by <emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis>:</para>


<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: <fvwmopt mod="FvwmTabs" opt="activeFG"/> <emphasis>color</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>The text color of the button for the visible tab. The default color is yellow.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: <fvwmopt mod="FvwmTabs" opt="activeBG"/> <emphasis>color</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>The backgound color of the button for the visible tab. The default color is MidnightBlue.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: <fvwmopt mod="FvwmTabs" opt="inactiveFG"/> <emphasis>color</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>The text color of the buttons for the invisible tabs. The default color is antiquewhite.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: <fvwmopt mod="FvwmTabs" opt="inactiveBG"/> <emphasis>color</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>The backgound color of the buttons for the invisible tabs. The default color is royalblue.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: <fvwmopt mod="FvwmTabs" opt="activeRelief"/> <emphasis>style</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>The relief style to use for active buttons. <emphasis>style</emphasis> can be either <emphasis>raised</emphasis>, <emphasis>flat</emphasis> or <emphasis>sunken</emphasis>. The default style is <emphasis>sunken</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>



<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: inactiveRelief <emphasis>style</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>The relief style to use for inactive buttons. <emphasis>style</emphasis> can be either <emphasis>raised</emphasis>, <emphasis>flat</emphasis> or <emphasis>sunken</emphasis>. The default style is <emphasis>flat</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: buttonYPadding <emphasis>pixels</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>How much padding to use around top and bottom of tab buttons. The default value is <emphasis>3</emphasis> pixels.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: pollRate <emphasis>ms</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Specifies how often to check for X events. <emphasis>ms</emphasis> is time in milliseconds. The default value, <emphasis>250</emphasis>, should be fine for most users. If you are on a very slow machine you may wish to increase this.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: buttonFont <emphasis>font</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> The font to use on the tab buttons. The default font is <emphasis>Helvetica -12 bold</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: titleFont <emphasis>font</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> The font to use on the titlebar. The default font is <emphasis>Helvetica -12</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: menuFont <emphasis>font</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> The font to use on the menus. The default font is <emphasis>Helvetica -12</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: fontSelector <emphasis>fontProgram</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> The external font chooser program to launch when dynamically changing fonts. The default <emphasis>fontProgram</emphasis> is <emphasis>gfontsel --print -f "%f"</emphasis>. Anti-gnome users might try <emphasis>xfontsel -print -pattern "%f"</emphasis>. If set to <emphasis>none</emphasis>, no font menu options will appear.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: autoSwallowClass <emphasis>className</emphasis> [<emphasis>tabManagerId</emphasis>], ...</term>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: autoSwallowResource <emphasis>resourceName</emphasis> [<emphasis>tabManagerId</emphasis>], ...</term>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: autoSwallowName <emphasis>name</emphasis> [<emphasis>tabManagerId</emphasis>], ...</term>
<listitem><simpara> Specify windows to swallow automatically. These are comma-separated lists that specify the class/resource/name of a window and an optional tab-manager id into which the window should be swallowed. By default, the tab-manager id increments from zero - ie. 0 is the first tab-manager created, 1 the second, etc, but it may be overriden by specifying an argument to the <emphasis>NewTabber</emphasis> function. (No whitespace is allowed in tabber ids.) You can alternatively specify 'any' or 'lastFocus' which will put the window in the tab-manager with the least number of tabs or the last focused tab-manager, respectively. If no tab-manager number is specified, an implicit default value of 'any' is used. Note that <emphasis>className</emphasis>/<emphasis>resourceName</emphasis>/<emphasis>name</emphasis> can be a (Perl) regular expression.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: balloonBG <emphasis>color</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> The backgound color of the balloon popups that appear over the tab buttons. The default color is <emphasis>#C0C080</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: balloonFont <emphasis>font</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> The font to use on the balloon popups. The default font is <emphasis>Helvetica -12</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: balloonWait <emphasis>ms</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> How long the mouse cursor must pause (in milliseconds) over a tab button before the balloon pops up. The default value is <emphasis>250</emphasis>. </simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: balloonMsg <emphasis>msg</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Message to display in balloon popups. The default value is <emphasis>%tabNo:\n%iconText\n%title</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: autoResize <emphasis>bool</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> <emphasis>bool</emphasis> can be either <emphasis>true</emphasis> or <emphasis>false</emphasis>. If true, windows in the tab-manager automatically resize to the dimensions of the largest window in the tab-manager. The default value is <emphasis>false</emphasis>. If the user performs an explicit resize of a tab-manager window, all windows in the tab-manager are resized to the new window size.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: stateFile <emphasis>file</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara><emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> has the ability to preserve its state (ie. remember the windows it has swallowed as tabs) b/w FVWM restarts. <emphasis>file</emphasis> specifies the name of a temporary file to record the state in, so it can be reconstructed when <emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> restarts. The default file is <envar>$FVWM_USERDIR</envar>/.fvwmtabs.state.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: fixedSizeTabs <emphasis>bool</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> <emphasis>bool</emphasis> can be either <emphasis>true</emphasis> or <emphasis>false</emphasis>. If true, the tab-manager will ensure each tab-button has the same dimensions. If false, the selected tab is expanded so that it is fully visible. The default value is <emphasis>false</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: showTitlebar <emphasis>bool</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Show internal titlebar. If set to <emphasis>true</emphasis> a titlebar appears below the row of tab-buttons and displays the title associated with the current window. This titlebar is capable of displaying long or multi-line titles. The default value is <emphasis>true</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: useTMTitlebar <emphasis>bool</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Add the title associated with the selected tab to the tab-manager titlebar. (ie. the titlebar at the top of the window, distinct from the titlebar below the tab-buttons.) Default value is <emphasis>true</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: dragDropIcon <emphasis>imageFile</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Specify the icon to display when performing a drag-&amp;-drop operation to reorder the tab-buttons. FvwmTabs will search the ImagePath for this image unless an absolute filename (ie. filename begins with '/') is specified. The default value is <emphasis>none</emphasis>. If <emphasis>none</emphasis> (or an invalid file) is specified a * is used.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: bBuggyFocus <emphasis>bool</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> FvwmTabs tries to work around a limitation in Perl/Tk (there is no way to access the timestamp associated with WM_TAKE_FOCUS events). On some systems this doesn't work and sometimes tab-managers have trouble acquiring the focus. If this happens to you, try setting this option to <emphasis>true</emphasis>. This can lead to focussing race-conditions (tab-managers temporarily "steal" focus in some situations) but this is less annoying than not being able to focus at all.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: enableSwallowDND <emphasis>bool</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Swallow windows that (are moved to) overlap a tabber.</simpara>
<simpara>Note: drag-&amp;-drop can be enabled for individual tabbers via the menu.
The default value is <emphasis>true</emphasis>.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: swallowDNDTolerance <emphasis>tol</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>Determines how much a window must overlap a tabber for it to be swallowed when drag-&amp;-drop is enabled. If the value has a %-sign appended to it, windows must overlap by the specified percentage of the current size of the tabber. If no %-sign is present, the value is treated in units of pixels. The default value is <emphasis>10</emphasis> (pixels).</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: useIconsOnTabs <emphasis>bool</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Show the mini icon associated with each window on its tab button. Note: mini icons for apps that use EWMH icons look a bit distorted.  This is because of the poor image resizing algorithm used in Tk. This sinactiveBG hould be rectified in the near future. The default value is <emphasis>true</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: killIcon <emphasis>image</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>Image to use on kill toolbar button. Default is <emphasis>none</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: addIcon <emphasis>image</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara>Image to use on add toolbar button. Default is <emphasis>none</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: swallowIcon <emphasis>image</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Image to use on add toolbar button when tabber will swallow next window to popup. Default is <emphasis>none</emphasis>. By using a separate icon to <emphasis>addIcon</emphasis>, this option provides visual feedback on when a tabber will unconditionally swallow the next window to popup.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: releaseIcon <emphasis>image</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Image to use on release toolbar button. Default is <emphasis>none</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>*FvwmTabs: menuIcon <emphasis>image</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Image to use on menu toolbar button. Default is <emphasis>none</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>


<section id="functions">
<title>Functions for Bindings</title>
<para>A number of FVWM functions are available once the FvwmTabs module is started.</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry>
<term>NewTabber</term>
<listitem><simpara> Create a new tabber. Optional argument is tabber name. No whitespace is allowed in the tabber name. Can also prefix --geometry argument. Example:</simpara>

<programlisting>
NewTabber --geometry=+200+400 scottie
</programlisting>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Tabize</term>
<listitem><simpara> Add a window (as a tab) to a tabber.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>NextTab</term>
<listitem><simpara> Show/select the next tab.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>PrevTab</term>
<listitem><simpara> Show/select the previous tab.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>LastTab</term>
<listitem><simpara> Show/select the last selected tab (if there was one).</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>ReleaseTab</term>
<listitem><simpara> Release a tabbed window back to FVWM.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>ReleaseIconifyTab</term>
<listitem><simpara> Release a tabbed window back to FVWM &amp; iconify it.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>ReleaseAllTabs</term>
<listitem><simpara> Release all windows in a tab-manager back to FVWM.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>ReleaseIconifyAllTabs</term>
<listitem><simpara> Release all windows in a tab-manager back to FVWM &amp; iconify them.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>CloseTabber</term>
<listitem><simpara> Destroy a tab-manager. All windows in the tab-manager are released back to FVWM.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>AddTab</term>
<listitem><simpara> Pick a new window to add to a tab-manager. Selecting this option &amp; clicking on a window will add the selected window to the tab-manager.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>MultiAddTab</term>
<listitem><simpara> Pick &amp; add new windows to a tab-manager until ESC is pressed.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>ShowTab <emphasis>tabNo</emphasis></term>
<listitem><simpara> Show/select tab <emphasis>tabNo</emphasis> in the tab-manager. <emphasis>tabNo</emphasis> is zero-based. ie. 0 is the first tab, 1 is the second, etc.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>AddToTabber</term>
<listitem><simpara> Add a window (as a tab) to a tab-manager.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>SwapLeft</term>
<listitem><simpara> Swap the selected window with the window on its immediate left.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>SwapRight</term>
<listitem><simpara> Swap the selected window with the window on its immediate right.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>SelectTabber</term>
<listitem><simpara> Select a tab-manager for a new window to be added to.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>EnableDND</term>
<listitem><simpara> Swallow windows that (are moved to) overlap a tabber.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>



<section id="keyBindings">
<title>Key Bindings</title>
<para>By default, <emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> reads a default user configuration file <filename>FvwmTabs-DefaultSetup</filename> which defines several useful key-bindings for <emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis>. You can tell <emphasis remap='B'>FvwmTabs</emphasis> NOT to read this file with:</para>
<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="SetEnv"/> FvwmTabs_NoDefaultSetup
</programlisting>
<para>This environment variable must be set <emphasis>before</emphasis> starting the module.
</para>Then, pressing Ctrl-Alt-a (when the focus is in a tab-manager) will allow you to click on a window to add to the tab-manager.

<para>All of the key bindings can be changed using the standard FVWM <fvwmref cmd="Key"/> command and making use of the aforementioned FVWM functions. ie.</para>
<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Key"/> (FvwmTabs*) A A CM <fvwmref cmd="Function"/> AddTab
</programlisting>

<para>Then, pressing Ctrl-Alt-a (when the focus is in a tab-manager) will allow you to click on a window to add to the tab-manager.</para>

<para>The default key bindings (set in the <filename>FvwmTabs-DefaultSetup</filename> file) are:</para>


<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-a</term>
<listitem><simpara> AddTab</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-c</term>
<listitem><simpara> CloseTabber</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-i</term>
<listitem><simpara> ReleaseIconifyTab</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-Shift-I</term>
<listitem><simpara> ReleaseIconifyAllTabs</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-l</term>
<listitem><simpara> LastTab</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-m</term>
<listitem><simpara> MultiAddTab</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-n &amp; Ctrl-Alt-Tab</term>
<listitem><simpara> NextTab</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-p</term>
<listitem><simpara> PrevTab</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-r</term>
<listitem><simpara> ReleaseTab</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-Shift-R</term>
<listitem><simpara> ReleaseAllTabs</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-t</term>
<listitem><simpara> NewTabber</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-I&lt;num&gt;</term>
<listitem><simpara> ShowTab &lt;num&gt;.</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-Left</term>
<listitem><simpara> SwapLeft</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Ctrl-Alt-Right</term>
<listitem><simpara> SwapRight</simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>




<section id="mouseBindings">
<title>Mouse Bindings</title>
<section id="tabMouseBindings">
<title>Mouse Bindings on Tab Buttons</title>
<para>Mouse-1 on a tab-button displays the window associated with the tab.</para>
<para>Mouse-2 on a tab-button releases the window associated with the tab back to the window manager as a standalone window.</para>
<para>Mouse-3 on a tab-button releases the window associated with the tab back to the window manager and iconifies it.</para>
<para>The tab-buttons can be reordered with a drag-&amp;-drop operation initiated with Ctrl-Mouse-2. A dragged tab is inserted before the tab-button onto which it is dropped.</para>
<para></para>
</section>
<section id="toolbarMouseBindings">
<title>Mouse Bindings on Toolbar Icons</title>
<para>Mouse-1 on the "menu" button will bring up a menu of options. See MENU BINDINGS. &fixme;</para>

<para>Mouse-1 on the "release" button will release the selected window from the tabber.</para>

<para>Mouse-2 on the "release" button will release all windows from the tabber, and iconify them.</para>

<para>Mouse-3 on the "release" button will release all windows from the tabber.</para>

<para>Mouse-1 on the "add" button will add the next window you click on to the tabber.</para>

<para>Mouse-2 on the "add" button will add the next window to popup to the tabber.</para>

<para>Mouse-3 on the "add" button will add every window you click on (until you press Esc) to the tabber.</para>

<para>Mouse-1 on the "kill" button will <fvwmref cmd="Close"/> the selected window.</para>

<para>Mouse-2 on the "kill" button causes FvwmTabs to try to kill the selected window itself.</para>

<para>Mouse-3 on the "kill" button will <fvwmref cmd="Destroy"/> the selected window.</para>

</section>
</section>


<section id="menu">
<title>Menu Options</title>
<para>Mouse-1 on the "menu" button will bring up a menu of options:</para>

<para>Release All will release all tabbed programs back to the window manager as standalone windows.</para>

<para>Release All (Iconify) will release all tabbed programs back to the window manager as iconised standalone windows.</para>

<para>Add will add the next mouse-clicked window to the tab-manager.</para>

<para>Add Next will add the next window that is created to the tab-manager.</para>

<para>Multi Add keeps adding mouse-clicked windows to a tab-manager until the escape key is pressed. Useful for adding multiple windows to a tab-manager at once.</para>

<para>Font shows a sub-menu enabling you to dynamically configure the button/title/menu fonts, using the external program identified by the <emphasis>fontSelector</emphasis> option.</para>

<para>Show Titlebar toggles the display of the titlebar below the tab-buttons.</para>

<para>Window Tabizer Dialog will popup a dialog box for specifying windows to swallow. Windows can be specified explicitly (by name) or by using a (Perl) regular expression matcher. (Note: / character is automatically escaped.)</para>

<para>The menu options between the separators will display the window/tab associated with the text. (The menu text is actually the title associated with the window. The text on each tab-button is the icon name.)</para>

<para>About pops up a dialog with version/developer information.</para>

<para>Close will close the FvwmTabs window, invoking Release All in the process.</para>
</section>


<section id="bugs">
<title>Known Bugs</title>
<simpara>Tab-managers don't take focus when iconified.</simpara>
<simpara>FvwmTabs doesn't obey <fvwmref cmd="ClickToFocus"/> mode.</simpara>
<simpara>FvwmTabs has a problem swallowing shaded windows.</simpara>
<simpara>Using <fvwmref cmd="Maximize"/> to resize tab-manager windows prevents dynamic resizing from working.</simpara>
<para>Please send bug reports, feature requests and queries about FvwmTabs to the FVWM Mailing list: <email>fvwm@fvwm.org</email>. Be sure to include the word "FvwmTabs" somewhere in the subject line.</para>
</section>

<section id="licence">
<title>Licence</title>
<para>FvwmTabs is GPL software.</para>
</section>

<section id="author">
<title>Author</title>
<para>Scott Smedley <email>ss@aao.gov.au</email></para>
</section>

</article>
