<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<!-- $Id$ -->

<section id='BugOpts'>
<title>BugOpts</title>

<cmdsynopsis>
	<command>BugOpts</command
	><arg choice='plain' rep='repeat'
		><arg choice='opt'
			><replaceable>option</replaceable
			><arg choice='opt'
				><replaceable>bool</replaceable
			></arg
		></arg
	>,</arg>
</cmdsynopsis>

<para>This command controls several workarounds for bugs in third party
programs.  The individual options are separated by commas.  The
optional argument
<replaceable>bool</replaceable>
is a boolean argument and controls if the bug workaround is
enabled or not.  It can either be "True" or "False" to turn the
option on or off, or "toggle" to switch is back and forth.  If
<replaceable>bool</replaceable>
is omitted, the default setting is restored.</para>

<para><fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="FlickeringMoveWorkaround"/>
disables ConfigureNotify events that are usually sent to an
application while it is moved.  If some windows flicker annoyingly
while being moved, this option may help you.  Note that if this
problem occurs it is not an fvwm bug, it is a problem of the
application.</para>

<para><fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="MixedVisualWorkaround"/>
makes fvwm install the root colormap before it does some
operations using the root window visuals.  This is only useful
when the
<option>-visual</option>
option is used to start fvwm and then only with some
configurations of some servers (e.g. Exceed 6.0 with an 8 bit
PseudoColor root and fvwm using a 24 bit TrueColor visual).</para>

<para>The
<fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="ModalityIsEvil"/>
option controls whether Motif applications have the ability to
have modal dialogs (dialogs that force you to close them first
before you can do anything else).  The default is to not allow
applications to have modal dialogs.  Use this option with
care. Once this option is turned on, you have to restart fvwm to
turn it off.</para>

<para><fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="RaiseOverNativeWindows"/>
makes fvwm try to raise the windows it manages over native windows
of the X server's host system.  This is needed for some X servers
running under Windows, Windows NT or Mac OS X.  Fvwm tries to detect if it
is running under such an X server and initializes the flag
accordingly.</para>

<para><fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="RaiseOverUnmanaged"/>
makes fvwm try to raise the windows it manages over
override_redirect windows.  This is used to cope with ill-mannered
applications that use long-lived windows of this sort, contrary to
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
conventions.  It is useful with the
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Unmanaged"/>
style option too.</para>

<para><fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="FlickeringQtDialogsWorkaround"/>
suppresses flickering of the focused window in some modules when
using <acronym>KDE</acronym> or <acronym>QT</acronym> applications with application modal dialog
windows.  By default this option is turned on.  This option may be
visually disturbing for other applications using windows not
managed by fvwm.  Since these applications are rare it is most
likely safe to leave this option at its default.</para>

<para><fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="QtDragnDropWorkaround"/>
suppresses the forwarding of unknown ClientEvent messages to windows --
usually this is harmless, but Qt has problems handling unrecognised
ClientEvent messages.  Enabling this option might therefore help for Qt
applications using DragnDrop.  This option is off by default.</para>

<para><fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="EWMHIconicStateWorkaround"/>
is needed by <acronym>EWMH</acronym> compliant pagers or taskbars which represent
windows which are on a different desktops as iconified. These
pagers and taskbars use a version of the <acronym>EWMH</acronym> specification before
version 1.2 (the current <acronym>KDE</acronym> 2 &amp; 3 versions).  These pagers and
taskbars use the IconicState WM_STATE state to determine if an
application is iconified.  This state, according to the
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>,
does not imply that a window is iconified (in the usual sense).
Turning on this option forces fvwm to establish an equivalence
between the IconicState WM_STATE state and the iconified window.
This violates
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
compliance but should not cause big problems.
By default this option is off.</para>

<para>With the
<fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="DisplayNewWindowNames"/>
enabled, fvwm prints the name, icon name (if available), resource
and class of new windows to the console.  This can help in finding
the correct strings to use in the
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/>
command.</para>

<para>When the
<fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="ExplainWindowPlacement"/>
option is enabled, fvwm prints a message to the console whenever a
new window is placed or one of the commands
<fvwmref cmd="PlaceAgain"/>,
<fvwmref cmd="Recapture"/> or
<fvwmref cmd="RecaptureWindow"/>
is used.  The message explains on which desk, page, Xinerama
screen and position it was placed and why.  This option can be
used to figure out why a specific window does not appear where you
think it should.</para>

<para>The
<fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="DebugCRMotionMethod"/>
option enables some debugging code in the ConfigureRequest
handling routines of fvwm.  It is not helpful for the user, but if
you report a bug to the fvwm team we may ask you to enable this
option.</para>

<para>The <fvwmopt cmd="BugOpts" opt="TransliterateUtf8"/> option
enables transliteration during conversions from utf-8 strings.  By
default fvwm will not transliterate during conversion, but will fall
back to alternate strings provided by the clients if conversion from
utf-8 fails due to characters which have no direct correspondence in
the target charecter set. Some clients however neglect to set non utf-8
properties correctly in which case this option may help.</para>

</section>
