<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<!-- $Id$ -->

<section id='EdgeResistance'>
<title>EdgeResistance</title>

<cmdsynopsis>
	<command>EdgeResistance</command>
	<arg choice='plain'><replaceable>scrolling</replaceable></arg>
	<arg choice='plain'><replaceable>moving</replaceable></arg>
	<arg choice='opt'><replaceable>xinerama-scrolling</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>

<para>Tells how hard it should be to change the desktop viewport by
moving the mouse over the edge of the screen and how hard it
should be to move a window over the edge of the screen.</para>

<para>The first parameter tells how many milliseconds the pointer must
spend on the screen edge before fvwm moves the viewport.  This is
intended for people who use</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="EdgeScroll"/> 100 100
</programlisting>

<para>but find themselves accidentally flipping pages when they do not
want to.</para>

<para>The second parameter tells how many pixels over the edge of the
screen a window's edge must move before it actually moves
partially off the screen.  By default the viewport is moved a full
page in the requested direction, but if you used
<fvwmref cmd="EdgeScroll"/>
and set any values other than zero they are used instead.</para>

<para>Note that, with</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="EdgeScroll"/> 0 0
</programlisting>

<para>it is still possible to move or resize windows across the edge of
the current screen.  By making the first parameter to
<emphasis remap='B'>EdgeResistance</emphasis>
10000 this type of motion is impossible.  With
<emphasis remap='B'>EdgeResistance</emphasis>
less than 10000 but greater than 0 moving over pages becomes
difficult but not impossible.  See also
<fvwmref cmd="EdgeThickness"/>.</para>

<para>The optional third parameter does the same as the second, but for
individual Xinerama screens.  If omitted,
<replaceable>xinerama-moving</replaceable>
is set to the value of
<replaceable>moving</replaceable>.
Set
<replaceable>xinerama-moving</replaceable>
to zero to ignore individual screen edges.  Note that the center of
the window being moved determines the xinerama screen on which the
window should be kept.</para>

</section>
