<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>


<section id='FakeClick'>
<title>FakeClick</title>

<cmdsynopsis>
	<command>FakeClick</command
	><arg choice='plain' rep='repeat'
		><optional
			><arg choice='plain'
				><replaceable>command</replaceable
			></arg
			><arg choice='plain'
				><replaceable>value</replaceable
			></arg
		></optional
	></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>

<para>This command is mainly intended for debugging fvwm and no
guarantees are made that it works for you.
<emphasis>FakeClick</emphasis>
can simulate mouse button press and release events and pass them
to fvwm or the applications.  The parameters are a list of
commands which consist of pairs of
<replaceable>command</replaceable>
tokens and integer
<replaceable>values</replaceable>,
The
<fvwmopt cmd="FakeClick" opt="press"/> and <fvwmopt cmd="FakeClick" opt="release"/>
commands are followed by the appropriate mouse button number and
generate a button press or release event on the window below the
pointer.  The
<fvwmopt cmd="FakeClick" opt="wait"/>
commands pauses fvwm for the given number of milliseconds.  The
<fvwmopt cmd="FakeClick" opt="modifiers"/>
command simulates pressing or releasing modifier keys.  The values
1 to 5 are mapped to
<keysym>Mod1</keysym>
to
<keysym>Mod5</keysym>
while 6, 7 and 8 are mapped to
<keysym>Shift</keysym>,
<keysym>Lock</keysym>
and
<keysym>Control</keysym>.
The modifier is set for any further button events.  To release a
modifier key, use the corresponding negative number.  The
<fvwmopt cmd="FakeClick" opt="depth"/>
command determines to which window the button events are
sent. With a depth of 1, all events go to the root window,
regardless of the pointer's position.  With 2, the event is passed
to the top level window under the pointer which is usually the
frame window. With 3, events go to the client window. Higher
numbers go to successive sub windows.  Zero (0) goes to the
smallest window that contains the pointer.  Note that events
propagate upward.</para>

<programlisting>
FakeClick depth 2 press 1 wait 250 release 1
</programlisting>

<para>This simulates a click with button 1 in the parent window (depth
2) with a delay of 250 milliseconds between the press and the
release.
Note: all command names can be abbreviated with their first letter.</para>


</section>
