<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<!-- $Id$ -->

<section id='GotoDesk'>
<title>GotoDesk</title>

<!--command-->
<cmdsynopsis>
	<command>GotoDesk</command>
	<group choice='opt'>
		<arg choice='plain'>prev</arg>
		<arg choice='plain'>
			<arg choice='plain'><replaceable>arg1</replaceable></arg>
			<arg choice='opt'><replaceable>arg2</replaceable></arg>
			<arg choice='opt'><replaceable>min</replaceable>
				<replaceable>max</replaceable></arg>
		</arg>
	</group>
</cmdsynopsis>
<!--/command-->

<para>
Switches the current viewport to another desktop (workspace, room).
</para>

<para>The command takes 1, 2, 3, or 4 arguments.  A single argument is
interpreted as a relative desk number.  Two arguments are
understood as a relative and an absolute desk number.  Three
arguments specify a relative desk and the minimum and maximum of
the allowable range. Four arguments specify the relative,
absolute, minimum and maximum values.  (Desktop numbers can be
negative).  If a literal
<fvwmopt cmd="GotoDesk" opt="prev"/>
is given as the single argument, the last visited desk number is
used.</para>

<para>If
<replaceable>arg1</replaceable>
is non zero then the next desktop number is the current desktop
number plus
<replaceable>arg1</replaceable>.</para>

<para>If
<replaceable>arg1</replaceable>
is zero then the new desktop number is
<replaceable>arg2</replaceable>.
(If
<replaceable>arg2</replaceable>
is not present, then the command has no effect.)</para>

<para>If
<replaceable>min</replaceable> and <replaceable>max</replaceable>
are given, the new desktop number is no smaller than
<replaceable>min</replaceable>
and no bigger than
<replaceable>max</replaceable>.
Values out of this range are truncated (if you gave an absolute
desk number) or wrapped around (if you gave a relative desk
number).</para>

<para>The syntax is the same as for
<fvwmref cmd="MoveToDesk"/>,
which moves a window to a different desktop.</para>

<para>The number of active desktops is determined dynamically.  Only
desktops which contain windows or are currently being displayed
are active.  Desktop numbers must be between 2147483647 and
-2147483648 (is that enough?).</para>

</section>
