<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<!-- $Id$ -->

<section id='configuration'>
<title>Configuration</title>
<section id='configuration_files'>
<title>Configuration Files</title>
<para>The configuration file is used to describe mouse and button
bindings, colors, the virtual display size, and related items.
The initialization configuration file is typically called
<filename>config</filename> (or <filename>.fvwm2rc</filename>).
By using the
<fvwmref cmd="Read"/>
command, it is easy to read in new configuration files as you go.</para>

<para>Lines beginning with '#' are ignored by fvwm.  Lines starting with '*'
are expected to contain module configuration commands (rather
than configuration commands for fvwm itself). Like in shell
scripts embedded newlines in a configuration file line can be
quoted by preceding them with a backslash.  All lines linked in
this fashion are treated as a single line.  The newline itself is
ignored.</para>

<para>Fvwm makes no distinction between configuration commands and
action commands, so anything mentioned in the fvwm commands
section can be placed on a line by itself for fvwm to execute as
it reads the configuration file, or it can be placed as an
executable command in a menu or bound to a mouse button or a
keyboard key.  It is left as an exercise for the user to decide
which function make sense for initialization and which ones make
sense for run-time.</para>

</section>

<section id='supplied_configuration'>
<title>Supplied Configuration</title>
<para>A sample configuration file,
<filename>system.fvwm2rc</filename>,
is supplied with the fvwm distribution.  It is well commented and
can be used as a source of examples for fvwm configuration.
It may be copied to <filename>/usr/local/share/fvwm/config</filename> file.</para>

<para>Alternatively, the built-in menu (accessible when no
configuration file is found) has options to create an initial
config file for the user.</para>

<para>If you are new to fvwm, try
<ulink url="http://fvwm-themes.sourceforge.net/">fvwm-themes</ulink>
package demonstrating the powerful fvwm functionality.</para>

</section>
</section>
