<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
]>

<section id='description'>
<title>Description</title>
<para>Fvwm is a window manager for X11.  It is designed to minimize
memory consumption, provide a 3D look to window frames, and a
virtual desktop.</para>

<para>Note that there are several window managers around that have
"fvwm" in their name.  In the past, version 2.x of fvwm was
commonly called fvwm2 to distinguish it from the former version
1.x (fvwm or even fvwm1).  Since version 1.x has been replaced by
version 2.x a long time ago we simply call version 2.x and all
versions to come, fvwm, throughout this document, and the
executable program is named fvwm.  There is an fvwm offspring
called fvwm95, it is mostly a patched version of fvwm-2.0.43.  The
main goal of fvwm95 was to supply a Windows 95 like look and
feel. Since then, fvwm has been greatly enhanced and practically
all fvwm95 features can be achieved by fvwm.</para>

<para>Fvwm provides both a large
<emphasis remap='I'>virtual desktop</emphasis>
and
<emphasis remap='I'>multiple disjoint desktops</emphasis>
which can be used separately or together.  The virtual desktop
allows you to pretend that your video screen is really quite
large, and you can scroll around within the desktop.  The multiple
disjoint desktops allow you to pretend that you really have
several screens to work at, but each screen is completely
unrelated to the others.</para>

<para>Fvwm provides
<emphasis remap='I'>keyboard accelerators</emphasis>
that allow you to perform most window manager functions,
including moving and resizing windows and operating the menus,
using keyboard shortcuts.</para>

<para>Fvwm has also overcome the distinction between configuration
commands and action commands that most window managers
make. Configuration commands typically set fonts, colors, menu
contents, and key and mouse function bindings, while action commands
do things like raise and lower windows.  Fvwm makes no such
distinction and allows anything to be changed at any time.</para>

<para>Other noteworthy differences between fvwm and other X11 window
managers are the introduction of the <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="SloppyFocus"/> and <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="NeverFocus"/>
focus methods.  Focus policy can be separately specified for
different window groups.  Windows using <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="SloppyFocus"/> acquire focus when the pointer moves into them and retain focus
until some other window acquires it.  Such windows do not lose
focus when the pointer moves into the root window.  The
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="NeverFocus"/>
policy is provided for use with windows into which one never types
(e.g. xclock, oclock, xbiff, xeyes, tuxeyes) - for example, if a
SloppyFocus terminal window has focus, moving the pointer over a
NeverFocus
decoration window does not deprive the terminal of focus.</para>

</section>
