<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<section id='extended_window_manager_hints'>
<title>Extended Window Manager Hints</title>
<para>Fvwm attempts to respect the extended window manager hints (ewmh
or <acronym>EWMH</acronym> for short) specification:
<ulink url='http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Standards_2fwm_2dspec'>http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Standards_2fwm_2dspec</ulink>
and some extensions of this specification.  This allows fvwm to
work with
<acronym>KDE</acronym>
version &gt;= 2,
<acronym>GNOME</acronym>
version 2 and other applications which respect this specification
(any application based on
<emphasis remap='SM'>GTK+</emphasis>
version 2). Applications which respect this specification are
called ewmh compliant applications.</para>

<para>This support is configurable with styles and commands.
These styles and commands have
<acronym>EWMH</acronym>
as the prefix (so you can find them easily in this man page).</para>

<para>There is a new Context 'D' for the
<fvwmref cmd="Key"/>,
<fvwmref cmd="PointerKey"/>,
<fvwmref cmd="Mouse"/> and
<fvwmref cmd="Stroke"/>
commands. This context is for desktop applications (such as
kdesktop and Nautilus desktop).</para>

<para>When a compliant taskbar asks fvwm to activate a window (typically
when you click on a button which represents a window in such a
taskbar), then fvwm calls the complex function
<emphasis remap='B'>EWMHActivateWindowFunc</emphasis>
which by default is Iconify Off, Focus and Raise. You can redefine
this function.  For example:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="DestroyFunc"/> EWMHActivateWindowFunc
<fvwmref cmd="AddToFunc"/> EWMHActivateWindowFunc I <fvwmref cmd="Iconify"/> Off
+ I <fvwmref cmd="Focus"/>
+ I <fvwmref cmd="Raise"/>
+ I <fvwmref cmd="WarpToWindow"/> 50 50
</programlisting>

<para>additionally warps the pointer to the center of the window.</para>

<para>The
<acronym>EWMH</acronym>
specification introduces the notion of Working Area.  Without ewmh
support the Working Area is the full visible screen (or all your
screens if you have a multi head setup and you use Xinerama).
However, compliant applications (such as a panel) can ask to
reserve space at the edge of the screen.  If this is the case, the
Working Area is your full visible screen minus these reserved
spaces. If a panel can be hidden by clicking on a button the
Working Area does not change (as you can unhide the panel at any
time), but the Dynamic Working Area is updated: the space reserved
by the panel is removed (and added again if you pop up the
panel). The Dynamic Working Area may be used when fvwm places or
maximizes a window.  To know if an application reserves space you
can type "xprop | grep _NET_WM_STRUT" in a terminal and select the
application.  If four numbers appear then these numbers define the
reserved space as explained in the
<fvwmref cmd="EwmhBaseStruts"/>
command.</para>

</section>
