<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<!-- $Id$ -->

<section id='fonts'>
<title>Fonts</title>
<section id='font_names_and_font_loading'>
<title>Font names and font loading</title>
<para>The fonts used for the text of a window title, icon titles, menus
and geometry window can be specified by using the Font and
IconFont <fvwmref cmd="Style"/>, the Font <fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle"/> and the <fvwmref cmd="DefaultFont"/>
commands. Also, all the Modules which use text have configuration
command(s) to specify font(s). All these styles and commands take
a font name as an argument. This section explains what is a font
name for fvwm and which fonts fvwm loads.</para>

<para>First, you can use what we can call a usual font name, for
example,</para>

<programlisting>
-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--10-100-75-75-m-60-ISO8859-1
-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--10-*
-*-fixed-medium-o-normal--14-*-ISO8859-15
</programlisting>

<para>That is, you can use an X Logical Font Description (XLFD for
short).  Then the "first" font which matches the description is
loaded and used. This "first" font depends of your font path and
also of your locale. Fonts which match the locale charset are
loaded in priority order. For example with</para>

<programlisting>
-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--10-*
</programlisting>

<para>if the locale charset is ISO8859-1, then fvwm tries to load a
font which matches</para>

<programlisting>
-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--10-*-ISO8859-1
</programlisting>

<para>with the locale charset ISO8859-15 fvwm tries to load</para>

<programlisting>
-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--10-*-ISO8859-15.
</programlisting>


<para>A font name can be given as an extended XLFD. This
is a comma separated list of (simple) XLFD font names, for example:</para>

<programlisting>
-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--14-*,-*-courier-medium-r-normal--14-*
</programlisting>

<para>Each simple font name is tried until a matching font with the
locale charset is found and if this fails each simple font name is
tried without constraint on the charset.</para>

<para>More details on the XLFD can be found in the X manual page, the X
Logical Font Description Conventions document (called xlfd) and
the XLoadFont and XCreateFontSet manual pages. Some useful font
utilities are: xlsfonts, xfontsel, xfd and xset.</para>

<para>If you have Xft support you can specify an Xft font name
(description) of a true type (or Type1) font prefixed by "xft:",
for example:</para>

<programlisting>
"xft:Luxi Mono"
"xft:Luxi Mono:Medium:Roman:size=14:encoding=iso8859-1"
</programlisting>

<para>The "first" font which matches the description is loaded.  This
first font depends on the XftConfig configuration file with Xft1
and on the /etc/fonts/fonts.conf file with Xft2.
One may read the Xft manual page and the fontconfig man page with
Xft2. The first string which follows "xft:" is always considered
as the family. With the second example Luxi Mono is the Family
(Other XFree TTF families: "Luxi Serif", "Luxi Sans"), Medium is
the Weight (other possible weights: Light, DemiBold, Bold, Black),
Roman is the slant or the style (other possibilities: Regular,
Oblique, Italic) size specifies the point size (for a pixel size
use pixelsize=), encoding allows for enforce a charset (iso8859-1
or iso10646-1 only; if no encoding is given the locale charset is
assumed).
An important parameter is "minspace=bool" where bool is True or
False. If bool is False (the default?) Xft gives a greater font
height to fvwm than if bool is True. This may modify text
placement, icon and window title height, line spacing in menus and
<fvwmref mod="FvwmIdent"/>, button height in some fvwm modules ...etc.  With a LCD
monitor you may try to add "rgba=mode" where mode is either rgb,
bgr, vrgb or vbgr to enable subpixel rendering. The best mode
depends on the way your LCD cells are arranged. You can pass other
specifications in between ":", as "foundry=foundry_name",
"spacing=type" where type can be monospace, proportional or
charcell, "charwidth=integer", "charheight=integer" or
"antialias=bool" where bool is True or False. It seems that these
parameters are not always taken in account.</para>

<para>To determine which Xft fonts are really loaded you can export
XFT_DEBUG=1 before starting fvwm and take a look to the error
log. With Xft2 you may use fc-list to list the available
fonts. Anyway, Xft support is experimental (from the X and the
fvwm point of view) and the quality of the rendering depends on
number of parameters (the XFree and the freetype versions and your
video card(s)).</para>

<para>After an Xft font name you can add after a ";" an XLFD
font name (simple or extended) as:</para>

<programlisting>
xft:Verdana:pixelsize=14;-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--14-*
</programlisting>

<para>then, if either loading the Xft font fails or fvwm has no Xft
support, fvwm loads the font
"-adobe-courier-bold-r-normal--14-*". This allows for writing
portable configuration files.</para>

</section>

<section id='font_and_string_encoding'>
<title>Font and string encoding</title>
<para>Once a font is loaded, fvwm finds its encoding (or charset) using
its name (the last two fields of the name). fvwm assumes that the
strings which are displayed with this font use this encoding (an
exception is that if an iso10646-1 font is loaded, then UTF-8 is
assumed for string encoding).
In a normal situation,
(i) a font is loaded by giving a font name without specifying the
encoding,
(ii) the encoding of the loaded font is the locale encoding, and
then
(iii) the strings in the fvwm configuration files should use the
locale encoding as well as the window and icon name. With Xft the
situation is bit different as Xft supports only iso10646-1 and
iso8859-1. If you do not specify one of these encodings in the Xft
font name, then fvwm does strings conversion using (iii). Note
that with multibyte fonts (and in particular with "CJK" fonts) for
good text rendering, the locale encoding should be the charset of
the font.</para>

<para>To override the previous rules, it is possible to specify the
string encoding in the beginning of a font description as follow:</para>

<programlisting>
StringEncoding=<replaceable>enc</replaceable>:_full_font_name_
</programlisting>

<para>where
<replaceable>enc</replaceable>
is an encoding supported by fvwm (usually font name charset plus some
unicode encodings: UTF-8, USC-2, USC-4 and UTF-16).</para>

<para>For example, you may use an iso8859-1 locale charset and have an
<fvwmref mod="FvwmForm"/> in Russian using koi8-r encoding. In this case, you just
have to ask <fvwmref mod="FvwmForm"/> to load a koi8-r font by specifying the
encoding in the font name. With a multibyte language, (as
multibyte font works well only if the locale encoding is the
charset of the font), you should use an iso10646-1 font:</para>

<programlisting>
StringEncoding=jisx0208.1983-0:-*-fixed-medium-r-*-ja-*-iso10646-1
</programlisting>

<para>or</para>

<programlisting>
"StringEncoding=jisx0208.1983-0:xft:Bitstream Cyberbit"
</programlisting>

<para>if your
<fvwmref mod="FvwmForm"/>
configuration uses jisx0208.1983-0 encoding. Another possibility
is to use UTF-8 encoding for your <fvwmref mod="FvwmForm"/> configuration and use
an iso10646-1 font:</para>

<programlisting>
-*-fixed-medium-r-*-ja-*-iso10646-1
</programlisting>

<para>or</para>

<programlisting>
"StringEncoding=UTF-8:xft:Bitstream Cyberbit"
</programlisting>

<para>or equivalently</para>

<programlisting>
"xft:Bitstream Cyberbit:encoding=iso10646-1"
</programlisting>

<para>In general iso10646-1 fonts together with UTF-8 string encoding
allows the display of any characters in a given menu, <fvwmref mod="FvwmForm"/>
etc.</para>

<para>More and more, unicode is used and text files use UTF-8
encoding. However, in practice the characters used range over your
locale charset (this is the case when you generate a menu with
fvwm-menu-desktop with recent versions of <acronym>KDE</acronym> and
<acronym>GNOME</acronym>). For
saving memory (an iso10646-1 font may have a very large number of
characters) or because you have a pretty font without an
iso10646-1 charset, you can specify the string encoding to be
UTF-8 and use a font in the locale charset:</para>

<programlisting>
StringEncoding=UTF-8:-*-pretty_font-*-12-*
</programlisting>


<para>In most cases, fvwm correctly determines the encoding of the
font. However, some fonts do not end with valid encoding
names. When the font name isn't normal, for example:</para>

<programlisting>
-misc-fixed-*--20-*-my_utf8-36
</programlisting>

<para>you need to add the encoding after the font name using a slash as
a delimiter. For example:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle"/> * <fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="Font"/> -misc-fixed-*--20-*-my_utf8-36/iso10646-1
</programlisting>

<para>If fvwm finds an encoding, fvwm uses the iconv system functions to
do conversion between encodings. Unfortunately, there are no
standards. For conversion between iso8859-1 and UTF-8: a GNU
system uses "ISO-8859-1" and other systems use "iso881" to define
the converters (these two names are supported by fvwm). Moreover,
in some cases it may be necessary to use machine specific
converters. So, if you experience problems you can try to get
information on your iconv implementation ("man iconv" may help)
and put the name which defines the converter between the font
encoding and UTF-8 at the end of the font name after the encoding
hint and a / (another possible solution is to use GNU
libiconv). For example use:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> * <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Font"/> -misc-fixed-*--14-*-iso8859-1/*/latin1
</programlisting>

<para>to use latin1 for defining the converter for the iso8859-1 encoding.
The "*" in between the "/" says to fvwm to determine the
encoding from the end of the font name. Use:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> * <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Font"/> -misc-fixed-*--14-*-local8859-6/iso8859-6/local_iso8859_6_iconv
</programlisting>

<para>to force fvwm to use the font with iso8859-6 as the encoding
(this is useful for bi-directionality)
and to use local_iso8859_6_iconv for defining the converters.</para>

</section>

<section id='font_shadow_effects'>
<title>Font Shadow Effects</title>
<para>Fonts can be given 3d effects. At the beginning of the font name
(or just after a possible StringEncoding specification) add</para>

<programlisting>
Shadow=<replaceable>size</replaceable> <optional><replaceable>offset</replaceable></optional> <optional><replaceable>directions]</replaceable></optional>:
</programlisting>

<para><replaceable>size</replaceable>
is a positive integer which specifies the number of pixels of shadow.
<replaceable>offset</replaceable>
is an optional positive integer which defines the number of pixels
to offset the shadow from the edge of the character.  The default
offset is zero.
<replaceable>directions</replaceable>
is an optional set of directions the shadow emanates from the
character.  The
<replaceable>directions</replaceable>
are a space separated list of fvwm directions:</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>N</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>North</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Top</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>t</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Up</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>u</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>-</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>E</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>East</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Right</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>r</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Right</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>r</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>]</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>S</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>South</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Bottom</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>b</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Down</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>d</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>_</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>W</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>West</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Left</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>l</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Left</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>l</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>[</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>NE</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>NorthEast</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>TopRight</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>tr</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>UpRight</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>ur</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>^</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>SE</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>SouthEast</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>BottomRight</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>br</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>DownRight</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>dr</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>&gt;</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>SW</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>SouthWest</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>BottomLeft</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>bl</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>DownLeft</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>dl</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>v</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>NW</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>NorthWest</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>TopLeft</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>tl</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>UpLeft</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>ul</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>&lt;</emphasis></para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>C</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Center</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>Centre</emphasis>, <emphasis>.</emphasis></para>

<para>A shadow is displayed in each given direction.
<emphasis remap='I'>All</emphasis>
is equivalent to all the directions.  The default
<replaceable>direction</replaceable>
is
<emphasis remap='I'>BottomRight</emphasis>.
With the
<emphasis remap='I'>Center</emphasis>
direction, the shadow surrounds the whole string.  Since this is a
super set of all other directions, it is a waste of time to
specify this along with any other directions.</para>

<para>The shadow effect only works with colorsets.  The color of the
shadow is defined by using the
<fvwmref cmd="Colorset" opt="fgsh"/>
option of the
<fvwmref cmd="Colorset"/>
command.  Please refer to the
<fvwmref sect="colorsets" opt="colorsets" name="Colorsets"/>
section for details about colorsets.</para>

<para>Note: It can be difficult to find the font,
<fvwmref cmd="Colorset" opt="fg"/>, <fvwmref cmd="Colorset" opt="fgsh"/> and <fvwmref cmd="Colorset" opt="bg"/>
colors to make this effect look good, but it can look quite good.</para>

</section>
</section>
