<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<section id='icccm_compliance'>
<title>ICCCM Compliance</title>

<para>Fvwm attempts to be
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
2.0 compliant.  Check
<ulink url='http://tronche.com/gui/x/icccm/'>http://tronche.com/gui/x/icccm/</ulink> for more info. In addition,
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
states that it should be possible for applications to receive any
keystroke, which is not consistent with the keyboard shortcut
approach used in fvwm and most other window managers.  In
particular you cannot have the same keyboard shortcuts working
with your fvwm and another fvwm running within Xnest (a nested X
server running in a window).  The same problem exists with mouse
bindings.</para>

<para>The
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
states that windows possessing the property</para>

<literallayout remap='.nf'>
WM_HINTS(WM_HINTS):
    Client accepts input or input focus: False
</literallayout>

<para>should not be given the keyboard input focus by the window
manager. These windows can take the input focus by themselves,
however.  A number of applications set this property, and yet
expect the window manager to give them the keyboard focus anyway,
so fvwm provides a window style,
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Lenience"/>, 
which allows fvwm to overlook this
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
rule.  Even with this window style it is not guaranteed that the
application accepts focus.</para>

<para>The differences between
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
1.1 and 2.0 include the ability to take over from a running
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
2.0 compliant window manager; thus</para>

<command>fvwm; vi ~/.fvwm/config; fvwm -replace</command>

<para>resembles the
<fvwmref cmd="Restart"/>
command.  It is not exactly the same, since killing the previously
running wm may terminate your X session, if the wm was started as
the last client in your
<markup>.Xclients</markup> or <markup>.Xsession</markup>
file.</para>

<para>Further additions are support for client-side colormap
installation (see the
<acronym>ICCCM</acronym>
for details) and the urgency hint. Clients can set this hint in
the WM_HINTS property of their window and expect the window manager
to attract the user's attention to the window.  Fvwm has two re-definable
functions for this purpose, "UrgencyFunc" and "UrgencyDoneFunc", which
are executed when the flag is set/cleared.  Their default definitions are:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="AddToFunc"/> UrgencyFunc
 + I <fvwmref cmd="Iconify"/> off
 + I <fvwmref cmd="FlipFocus"/>
 + I <fvwmref cmd="Raise"/>
 + I <fvwmref cmd="WarpToWindow"/> 5p 5p
<fvwmref cmd="AddToFunc"/> UrgencyDoneFunc
 + I <fvwmref cmd="Nop"/>
</programlisting>

</section>
