<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../fvwm.ent" >
%myents;
]>


<section id='menus'>
<title>Menus</title>

<para>Before a menu can be opened, it has to be populated with menu
items using the
<fvwmref cmd="AddToMenu"/>
command and bound to a key or mouse button with the
<fvwmref cmd="Key"/>,
<fvwmref cmd="PointerKey"/> or
<fvwmref cmd="Mouse"/>
command (there are many other ways to invoke a menu too).  This is
usually done in the configuration file.</para>

<para>Fvwm menus are extremely configurable in look and feel.  Even the
slightest nuances can be changed to the user's liking, including
the menu item fonts, the background, delays before popping up sub
menus, generating menus dynamically and many other features.
Please refer to the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle"/>
command to learn more.</para>

<section id="menu_types">
<title>Types of Menus</title>

<para>In fvwm there are four slightly different types of menus:</para>

<para><fvwmref cmd="Popup"/> menus
can appear everywhere on the screen on their own or attached to a
part of a window.  The
<fvwmref cmd="Popup"/>
command opens popup menus.  If the popup menu was invoked with a
mouse button held down, it is closed when the button is released.
The item under the pointer is then activated and the associated
action is executed.</para>

<para><fvwmref cmd="Menu"/>
is a very similar command, but the menus it opens are slightly less
transient.  When invoked by clicking a mouse button, it stays open
and can be navigated with no button held.  But if it is invoked by
a button press followed by mouse motion, it behaves exactly like a
popup menu.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Tear off menus</emphasis> or <emphasis remap='I'>Pin up menus</emphasis>
are menus from either of the above two commands that have been
"torn off" their original context and pinned on the desktop like a
normal window.  They are created from other menus by certain key
presses or mouse sequences or with the
<fvwmref cmd="TearMenuOff"/>
command from inside a menu.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Sub menus</emphasis>
are menus inside menus.  When a menu item that has the
<fvwmref cmd="Popup"/>
command as its action is selected, the named menu is opened as an
inferior menu to the parent.  Any type of menu can have sub menus.</para>
</section>


<section id="menu_anatomy">
<title>Menu Anatomy</title>

<para>Menus consist of any number of titles which are inactive menu
items that usually appear at the top of the menu, normal items
triggering various actions when selected, separator lines between
the items, tear off bars (a horizontal broken line) that tear off
the menu when selected, and sub menu items indicated with a
triangle pointing left or right, depending on the direction in
which the sub menu appears.  All the above menu items are
optional.</para>

<para>Additionally, if the menu is too long to fit on the screen, the
excess menu items are put in a continuation menu and a sub menu
with the string "More..." is placed at the bottom of the menu. The
"More..." string honors the locale settings.</para>

<para>Finally, there may be a picture running up either side of the menu
(a "side bar").</para>

</section>




<section id="menu_navigation">
<title>Menu Navigation</title>

<para>Menus can be navigated either with the keyboard or with the
mouse.  Many people prefer to use the mouse, but it can be rather
tedious.  Once you get the hang of it, keyboard navigation can be
much faster.  While fvwm displays a menu, it can do nothing else.
For example, new windows do not appear before the menu is closed.
However, this is not exactly true for tear off menus.  See the
<fvwmref sect="menus" opt="tearoff_menus" name="Tear Off Menus"/>
section for details.</para>

</section>



<section id="mouse_navigation">
<title>Mouse Navigation</title>

<para>Moving the pointer over a menu selects the item below it.
Normally this is indicated by a 3d border around the item, but not
all parts of a menu can be selected.  Pressing any mouse button
while a menu is open by default activates the item below it.  Items of a
popup menu are also activated by releasing a held mouse button.
In case of an item that hides a sub menu, the sub menu is
displayed if the pointer hovers over the item long enough or moves
close to the triangle indicating the sub menu.  This behaviour can
be tuned with menu styles.</para>

<para>Scrolling a mouse wheel over a menu either wraps the pointer along the
menu (default), scrolls the menu under the pointer or act as if the
menu was clicked depending on the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="MouseWheel"/> menu style.</para>

<para>Clicking on a selected item activates it - what happens exactly
depends on the type of the item.</para>

<para>Clicking on a title, a separator, the side bar, or outside the
menu closes the menu (exception:  tear off menus can not be closed
this way).  Pressing mouse button 2 over a menu title or
activating a tear off bar creates a tear off menu from the current
menu.  Clicking on a normal menu item invokes the command that is
bound to it, and clicking on a sub menu item either closes all
open menus and replaces them with the sub menu or posts the menu
(default).</para>

<para>Posting menus is meant to ease mouse navigation.  Once a sub menu
is posted, only items from that sub menu can be selected.  This
can be very useful to navigate the menu if the pointer tends to
stray off the menu.  To unpost the menu and revert back to normal
operation, either click on the same sub menu item or press any
key.</para>

</section>




<section id="keyboard_navigation">
<title>Keyboard Navigation</title>

<para>Just like with mouse navigation, the item below the pointer is
selected.  This is achieved by warping the pointer to the menu
items when necessary.  While a menu is open, all key presses are
intercepted by the menu.  No other application can get keyboard
input (although this is not the case for tear off menus).</para>

<para>Items can be selected directly by pressing a hotkey that can be
configured individually for each menu item.  The hotkey is
indicated by underlining it in the menu item label.  With the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="AutomaticHotkeys"/>
menu style fvwm automatically assigns hotkeys to all menu items.</para>

<para>The most basic keys to navigate through menus are the cursor keys
(move up or down one item, enter or leave a sub menu),
<keysym>Space</keysym>
(activate item) and
<keysym>Escape</keysym>
(close menu).  Numerous other keys can be used to navigate through
menus by default:</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Enter</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Return</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Space</emphasis>
activate the current item.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Escape</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Delete</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-G</emphasis>
exit the current sequence of menus or destroy a tear off menu.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>J</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>N</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Cursor-Down</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Tab</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Meta-Tab</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-F</emphasis>,
move to the next item.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>K</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>P</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Cursor-Up</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-Tab</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-Meta-Tab</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-B</emphasis>,
move to the prior item.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>L</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Cursor-Right</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>F</emphasis>
enter a sub menu.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>H</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Cursor-Left</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>B</emphasis>
return to the prior menu.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-Cursor-Up</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-K</emphasis>
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-P</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-Ctrl-Meta-Tab</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Page-Up</emphasis>
move up five items.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-Cursor-Down</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-J</emphasis>
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-N</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-Meta-Tab</emphasis>
<emphasis remap='I'>Page-Down</emphasis>
move down five items.</para>

<para>
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-P</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Home</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-Cursor-Up</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-A</emphasis>
move to the first item.</para>

<para>
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-N</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>End</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-Cursor-Down</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-E</emphasis>
move to the last item.</para>

<para>
<emphasis remap='I'>Meta-P</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Meta-Cursor-Up</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-Cursor-Left</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Shift-Ctrl-Tab</emphasis>,
move up just below the next separator.</para>

<para>
<emphasis remap='I'>Meta-N</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Meta-Cursor-Down</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-Cursor-Right</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Ctrl-Tab</emphasis>,
move down just below the next separator.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Insert</emphasis>
opens the "More..." sub menu if any.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Backspace</emphasis>
tears off the menu.</para>
</section>

<section id="menu_bindings">
<title>Menu Bindings</title>

<para>The keys and mouse buttons used to navigate the menu can be configured
using the
<fvwmref cmd="Key"/>
and
<fvwmref cmd="Mouse"/>
commands with the special context 'M', possible combined with 'T' for
the menu title, 'I' for other menu items, 'S' for any border or
sidepic, '[' for left border including a left sidepic, ']' for right
border including a right sidepic, '-' for top border, '_' for bottom
border.  The menu context uses its own set of actions that can be bound
to keys and mouse buttons.  These are
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuClose</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuEnterContinuation</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuEnterSubmenu</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuLeaveSubmenu</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuMoveCursor</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuCursorLeft</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuCursorRight</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuSelectItem</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuScroll</emphasis> and
<emphasis remap='I'>MenuTearOff</emphasis>.</para>

<para>It is not possible to override the key Escape with no modifiers for
closing the menu. Neither is it possible to undefine mouse button 1,
the arrow keys or the enter key for minimal navigation.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuClose</emphasis>
exits from the current sequence of menus or destroys a tear off menu.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuEnterContinuation</emphasis>
opens the "More..." sub menu if any.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuEnterSubmenu</emphasis>
enters a sub menu.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuLeaveSubmenu</emphasis>
returns to the prior menu.</para>


<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuMoveCursor</emphasis>
<replaceable>n</replaceable>
<optional><replaceable>m</replaceable></optional>
moves the selection to another item.  If the first argument is zero
the second argument specifies an absolute item in the menu to move
the pointer to. Negative items are counted from the end of the menu.
If the first argument is non-zero, the second argument must be omitted,
and the first argument specifies a relative change in the selected item.
The positions may be suffixed with a 's' to indicate that the items should
refer only to the first items after separators.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuCursorLeft</emphasis>
enters a sub menu with the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="SubmenusLeft"/>
menu style, and returns to the prior menu with the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="SubmenusRight"/> menu style.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuCursorRight</emphasis>
enters a sub menu with the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="SubmenusRight"/>
menu style, and returns to the prior menu with the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="SubmenusLeft"/> menu style.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuSelectItem</emphasis>
triggers the action for the menu item.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuScroll </emphasis><replaceable>n</replaceable>
performs menu scrolling according to the
<fvwmref cmd="MenuStyle" opt="MouseWheel"/> menu style with
<replaceable>n</replaceable> items.  The distance can be
suffixed with an 's' to indicate the items should refer only to the
first items after separators.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>MenuTearOff</emphasis>
turns a normal menu into a "torn off" menu. See
<fvwmref sect="menus" opt="tearoff_menus" name="Tear Off Menus"/>
for details.</para>

</section>



<section id="tearoff_menus">
<title>Tear Off Menus</title>

<para>A tear off menu is any menu that has been "torn off" the window it
was attached to and pinned to the root window.  There are three
ways to tear off a menu:  click on the menu title with mouse
button 2, press
<keysym>Backspace</keysym>
in the menu or activate its tear off bar (a horizontal bar with a
broken line).  Tear off bars must be added to the menu as any
other item by assigning them the command
<fvwmref cmd="TearMenuOff"/>.</para>

<para>The builtin tear off actions can be overridden by undefining the
builtin menu actions bound to tear off. To remove the builtin mouse
button 2 binding, use:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Mouse"/> 2 MT A -
</programlisting>

<para>and to remove the builtin backspace binding, use:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Key"/> Backspace M A -
</programlisting>

<para>See the section
<fvwmref sect="menus" opt="menu_bindings" name="Menu Bindings"/>
for details on how to assign other bindings for tear off.</para>

<para>Note that prior to fvwm 2.5.20 the tear off mouse bindings were
redefined in different way, which no longer work.</para>


<para>The window containing the menu is placed as any other window would
be.  If you find it confusing to have your tear off menus appear
at random positions on the screen, put this line in your
configuration file:</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> fvwm_menu <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="UsePPosition"/>
</programlisting>


<para>To remove borders and buttons from a tear-off menu but keep the
menu title, you can use</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> fvwm_menu !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 0, !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 1
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> fvwm_menu !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 2, !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 3
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> fvwm_menu !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 4, !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 5
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> fvwm_menu !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 6, !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 7
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> fvwm_menu !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 8, !<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Button"/> 9
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> fvwm_menu <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Title"/>, <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="HandleWidth"/> 0
</programlisting>


<para>A tear off menu is a cross breeding between a window and a menu.
The menu is swallowed by a window and its title is stripped off
and displayed in the window title.  The main advantage is that the
menu becomes permanent - activating an item does not close the
menu.  Therefore, it can be used multiple times without reopening
it.  To destroy such a menu, close its window or press the
<keysym>Escape</keysym>
key.</para>

<para>Tear off menus behave somewhat differently than normal menus and
windows.  They do not take the keyboard focus, but while the
pointer is over one of them, all key presses are sent to the
menu.  Other fvwm key bindings are disabled as long as the pointer
is inside the tear off menu or one of its sub menus.  When the
pointer leaves this area, all sub menus are closed immediately.
Note that the window containing a tear off menu is never hilighted
as if it had the focus.</para>

<para>A tear off menu is an independent copy of the menu it originated
from.  As such, it is not affected by adding items to that menu or
changing its menu style.</para>

<para>To create a tear off menu without opening the normal menu first,
the option
<fvwmref cmd="Menu" opt="TearOffImmediately"/>
can be added to the
<fvwmref cmd="Menu"/> or <fvwmref cmd="Popup"/>
command.</para>
</section>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="AddToMenu.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="ChangeMenuStyle.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="CopyMenuStyle.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="DestroyMenu.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="DestroyMenuStyle.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="Menu.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="MenuStyle.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="Popup.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="TearMenuOff.xml" />
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="Title.xml" />


</section>
