<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
]>

<section id='virtual_desktop'>
<title>The Virtual Desktop</title>
<para>Fvwm provides multiple virtual desktops for users who wish to use
them.  The screen is a viewport onto a
<emphasis remap='I'>desktop</emphasis>
which may be larger than the screen.  Several distinct desktops
can be accessed (concept: one desktop for each project, or one
desktop for each application, when view applications are
distinct).  Since each desktop can be larger than the physical
screen, divided into m by n
<emphasis remap='I'>pages</emphasis>
which are each the size of the physical screen, windows which are
larger than the screen or large groups of related windows can
easily be viewed.</para>

<para>The (m by n) size (i.e. number of pages) of the virtual desktops
can be changed any time, by using the
<fvwmref cmd="DesktopSize"/>
command.  All virtual desktops must be (are) the same
size.  The total number of distinct desktops does not need to be
specified, but is limited to approximately 4 billion total. All
windows on a range of desktops can be viewed in the
<fvwmref mod="FvwmPager"/>,
a miniature view of the desktops.  The pager is an accessory
program, called a module, which is not essential for the window
manager to operate.  Windows may also be listed using the
<fvwmref cmd="WindowList"/>
command or the
<fvwmref mod="FvwmIconMan"/>
module.</para>

<para>Fvwm keeps the windows on the desktop in a layered stacking order;
a window in a lower layer never obscures a window in a higher
layer. The layer of a window can be changed by using the
<fvwmref cmd="Layer"/>
command.  The concept of layers is a generalization of the
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="StaysOnTop"/>
flag of older fvwm versions. The
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="StaysOnTop"/> and
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="StaysPut"/>
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/>
options are now implemented by putting the windows in suitable
layers and the previously missing
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="StaysOnBottom"/>
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/>
option has been added.</para>

<para>
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="Sticky"/>
windows are windows which transcend the virtual desktop by
"Sticking to the screen's glass".  They always stay put on the
screen. This is convenient for things like clocks and xbiffs, so
you only need to run one such gadget and it always stays with you.
Icons can also be made to stick to the glass, if desired.</para>

<para>Window geometries are specified relative to the current viewport.
That is:</para>

<command>xterm -geometry +0+0</command>

<para>creates a window in the upper left hand corner of the visible
portion of the screen.  It is permissible to specify geometries
which place windows on the virtual desktop, but off the screen.
For example, if the visible screen is 1000 by 1000 pixels, and the
desktop size is 3x3, and the current viewport is at the upper left
hand corner of the desktop, invoking:</para>

<command>xterm -geometry +1000+1000</command>

<para>places a window just off of the lower right hand corner of the
screen.  It can be found by moving the mouse to the lower right
hand corner of the screen and waiting for it to scroll into view.
A geometry specified as something like:</para>

<command>xterm -geometry -5-5</command>

<para>places the window's lower right hand corner 5 pixels from the
lower right corner of the visible portion of the screen.  Not all
applications support window geometries with negative offsets.
Some applications place the window's upper right hand corner 5
pixels above and to the left of the upper left hand corner of the
screen; others may do just plain bizarre things.</para>

<para>There are several ways to cause a window to map onto a desktop or
page other than the currently active one. The geometry technique
mentioned above (specifying x,y coordinates larger than the
physical screen size), however, suffers from the limitation of
being interpreted relative to the current viewport: the window may
not consistently appear on a specific page, unless you always
invoke the application from the same page.</para>

<para>A better way to place windows on a different page, screen or desk
from the currently mapped viewport is to use the
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="StartsOnPage"/> or
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="StartsOnScreen"/>
style specification (the successors to the older
<fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="StartsOnDesk"/>
style) in your
<filename>config</filename>
file.  The placement is consistent: it does
not depend on your current location on the virtual desktop.</para>

<para>Some applications that understand standard Xt command line
arguments and X resources, like xterm and xfontsel, allow the user
to specify the start-up desk or page on the command line:</para>

<command>xterm -xrm "*Desk:1"</command>

<para>starts an xterm on desk number 1;</para>

<command>xterm -xrm "*Page:3 2 1"</command>

<para>starts an xterm two pages to the right and one down from the upper
left hand page of desk number 3.  Not all applications understand
the use of these options, however.  You could achieve the same
results with the following lines in your
<filename>.Xdefaults</filename>
file:</para>

<command>XTerm*Desk: 1</command>

<para>or</para>

<command>XTerm*Page: 3 2 1</command>

</section>
