<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
]>

<section id='xinerama_support'>
<title>Xinerama Support</title>
<para>Fvwm supports the Xinerama extension of newer X servers
which is similar to multi head support (multiple screens) but
allows one to move windows between screens.  If Xinerama support has
been compiled into fvwm, it is used whenever fvwm runs on an X
server that supports and uses multiple screens via Xinerama.
Without this option, the whole desktop is treated as one big
screen.  For example, menus might pop up right between two
screens.  The <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="EdgeResistance"/> option
of the <fvwmref cmd="Style"/> command command allows for specifying
an explicit resistance value for moving windows over the screen
edge between two Xinerama screens. Xinerama support can be enabled
or disabled on the fly or from the configuration file with the
<fvwmref cmd="Xinerama"/> command.  Many modules and commands work
nicely with Xinerama displays.</para>

<para>Whenever a geometry in the usual X format can be supplied,
fvwm's Xinerama extension allows for specifying a screen in addition
to the geometry (or even the screen alone).  To do this, a '@' is
added to the end of the geometry string followed by either the
screen number or a letter.  A number is taken as the number of the
Xinerama screen to be used (as configured in the X server).  The
letter can be one of 'g' for the global screen (the rectangle that
encloses all Xinerama screens), 'p' for the primary screen (see
below), 'c' for the current screen (the one that currently
contains the pointer).  If the X server does not support Xinerama
or only one screen is used, the screen bit is ignored.</para>


<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="Style"/> * <fvwmref cmd="Style" opt="IconBox"/> 64x300-0-0@p
</programlisting>


<para>Xinerama support can be configured to use a primary screen.  Fvwm
can be configured to place new windows and icons on this screen.
The primary screen is screen 0 by default but can be changed with
the
<fvwmref cmd="XineramaPrimaryScreen"/>
command.</para>

<para>Xinerama support was designed to work out of the box with the same
configuration file that would work on a single screen.  It may
not perform very well if the involved screens use different screen
resolutions.  In this situation, windows may get stuck in the
portion of the whole desktop that belongs to neither screen.  When
this happens, the windows or icons can be retrieved with the
command</para>

<programlisting>
<fvwmref cmd="All"/> <fvwmref cmd="MoveToScreen"/>
</programlisting>


<para>that can be entered in an <fvwmref mod="FvwmConsole"/> window or
with <fvwmref mod="FvwmCommand"/>.</para>

<para>For multi-screen implementations other than Xinerama, such as
Single Logical Screen, it is possible to simulate a Xinerama
configuration if the total screen seen by fvwm is made up of
equal sized monitors in a rectangular grid.  The commands
<fvwmref cmd="XineramaSls"/>, <fvwmref cmd="XineramaSlsSize"/> and <fvwmref cmd="XineramaSlsScreens"/>
are used to configure this feature.</para>

</section>
